Guide to the Records of the Office of the President (Oliva) RG.3.0.11
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the President (Oliva)
1960-2007
1987-2002
New York University Archives
Oliva, L. Jay (Lawrence Jay), 1933-2014
New York University
RG.3.0.11
63.9 Linear Feet in 131 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, 8 oversized flat boxes, and 1 media box
L. Jay Oliva (1933-2014) began his career at New York University as a professor of Russian history. He was president of NYU from 1991 to 2002 after spending more than three decades in academic and administrative positions at the University. In addition, Oliva was the co-founder of the George H. Heyman, Jr. Center for Philanthropy and Fundraising and he served as executive producer and chair of the Skirball Center for the Performing Arts. The Records of the Office of the President (Oliva) consist of materials created and collected by Oliva before, during, and after his presidential tenure. These materials include correspondence, speeches and writing, event programs and invitations, reports, and meeting minutes.
Conditions Governing Access
Governance records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Series VI. Governance is closed until 2037.
The following series is closed and access is restricted:
Series IV. Development and Finance
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were transferred from the Office of the President in multiple installments. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 14.019, 98.027, 99.019, 02.009, 00.002, 04.009, 00.006, 01.017, and 02.013.
Appraisal
Floppy disks were deaccessioned because they contained duplicate materials already present in the collection. A list of deaccessioned books and journals is available in the collection file.
Arrangement
The records are arranged into 11 series, one of which has been further arranged into subseries. The series and subseries arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Writing and Speeches
Subseries II.A Writing
Subseries II.B Speeches
Series III. Administrative Files
Series IV. Associations
Series V. Development and Finance
Series VI. Events and Programs
Series VII. Governance
Series VIII. Schools, Offices, and Divisions
Series IX. Publicity
Series X. Art and Memorabilia
Series XI. Subject Files
Biographical Note
Born in Walden, New York, on September 23, 1933, L. Jay Oliva (1933-2014) received his B.A. from Manhattan College in 1955, and his M.A. (1957) and Ph.D. (1960) from Syracuse University. He began his career at New York University (NYU) in 1960, as a night school history lecturer, becoming a full professor of history in 1969. Around this time, he began to take on administrative responsibilities in addition to his academic duties. From 1970 to 1975, he served as Deputy Vice Chancellor, and from 1971-1972, as Dean of Faculty for the University College of Arts and Science. He then became Vice President for Academic Planning and Services (1975-1977), Vice President for Academic Affairs (1977-1980), Provost and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs (1980-1983), Chancellor and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs (1983-1990), and finally, President (1991-2002). In addition, Oliva was the co-founder of the George H. Heyman, Jr. Center for Philanthropy and Fundraising and he served as executive producer and chair of the Skirball Center for the Performing Arts.
In 1990, the NYU Board of Trustees unanimously elected Oliva as the successor to John Brademas and NYU's 14th president. On November 21, 1991, Oliva became the first faculty member in the institution's 163-year history to be elevated to this position. Oliva's presidential tenure was marked by a major fundraising drive, started by John Brademas, and completed by Oliva five years early. He also completed a second $1 billion campaign in five years. Oliva also focused on transforming NYU from a commuter school into a global university by hiring well-known professors and offering more foreign-study programs. Applications tripled during his tenure. As president, Oliva continued to teach Russian history and served on various boards and committees, including the Institute of International Education (IIE), the University Athletic Association (UAA), and the League of World Universities, for which he was the main organizer. Prior to becoming the president of NYU, Oliva published two books, Misalliance: A Study of French Policy in Russia During the Seven Years' War (1964) and Russia in the Era of Peter the Great (1969); and various articles, including many related to sports, such as "How to Clean Up College Sports (The Washington Post, November 20, 1986), and others related to university-issues, such as "The Dorming of New York City" (The New York Times, January 28, 1989), among others. Oliva was the recipient of numerous awards, such as the Ellis Island Medal of Honor (1992) and a National Italian American Foundation honor (1994), and honorary degrees from Tel Aviv University and Hebrew Union College, among others.
Oliva passed away in 2014.
Sources cited:
Martin, Douglas. "L. Jay Oliva, Who Led the Rise of N.Y.U. in the '90s, Dies at 80." The New York Times. April 22, 2014. https://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/23/nyregion/l-jay-oliva-who-led-the-rise-of-nyu-dies-at-80.html.
Related Materials
For additional information on L. Jay Oliva, see also the Administrative Records of L. Jay Oliva (RG 6.0.8).
Scope and Contents
The Records of the Office of the President (Oliva), 1960-2007, include the day-to-day operations and pursuits of the President's office under L. Jay Oliva's tenure. The collection consists of materials created and collected by Oliva before, during, and after his presidential tenure, encompassing his long career at NYU and exhibiting how his viewpoints were shaped over time. Materials include correspondence, speeches and writing, reports, meeting minutes, and publications from various departments and schools. There are fundraising materials (grant applications and reports, donor briefings, and budgets) which demonstrate Oliva's focus on campaigns and appeals during his term. Additionally, there are memos to departmental heads and committees; announcements and press releases; event materials (invitations, programs, and agendas); travel itineraries; reports to various stakeholders; and correspondence and related materials with other organizations (outside of NYU) on which Oliva served as a board member or committee participant. Many of these items, such as the event programs, speeches, and publicity materials, exhibit Oliva's goal of transforming NYU into a global university since they include the dedication of new or enhanced programs abroad (such as NYU in London and the various events at Villa La Pietra). The collection also includes memorabilia (commencement robe, plaques, and pins), artwork, and photographs.
Clippings (information artifacts); College Presidents -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Education, Higher -- New York (N.Y.); Education -- New York (State) -- New York.; Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Private universities and colleges -- Administration -- United States.; Reports.; Speeches.; Universities and colleges |x Departments.; New York University; New York University
- Series I. Correspondence, 1985-2002; 10.5 Linear Feet in 24 manuscript boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series reflects Oliva's presidential responsibility to regularly communicate, internally and externally, about the University. It consists of general and daily correspondence. Most of the correspondence is from individuals and organizations outside of NYU, although there is a significant amount of correspondence from alumni and parents of current students. Additionally, there are "Letters to the University Community," which allowed him to communicate directly with everyone connected to the University.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, January-September 1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October-November 1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, December 1990 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Correspondence, January 1991 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February-March 1991 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July-September 1991 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, October 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, November 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, December 1991 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February-March 1992 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May-July 1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1992 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, October 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, November 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, December 1992 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January 1993 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, February 1993 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March 1993 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1993 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 1993 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 1993 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, July-August 1993 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, September 1993 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 1993 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November 1993 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, December 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January 1994 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, February 1994 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, March 1994 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, April 1994 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, May 1994 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - Correspondence, June 1994 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July 1994 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, August 1994 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September 1994 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October-November 1994 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, December 1994 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1995 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March-April 19935 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May-June 1995 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, July-August 1995 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September-October 1995 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1995 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1996 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, March 1996 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, April-May 1996 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, June-July 1996 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1996 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, October-November 1996 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, December 1996 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1997 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, March 1997 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, April 1997 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, May 1997 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, June-July 1997 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1997 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, October 1997 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, November-December 1997 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1998 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March 1998 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, April 1998 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 1998 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 1998 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July 1998 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, August-September 1998 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October-November 1998 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, December 1998 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January-February 1999 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, March 1999 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, April 1999 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May 1999 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, June 1999 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, July 1999 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, August 1999 (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September 1999 (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October 1999 (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, November 1999 (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, December 1999 (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 2000 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February 2000 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2000 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 2000 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June-July 2000 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, August-September 2000 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, October 2000 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, November 2000 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, December 2000 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, January 2001 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, February 2001 (Box 22, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2001 (Box 22, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, May 2001 (Box 22, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, June 2001 (Box 22, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, July-August 2001 (Box 23, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, September 2001 (Box 23, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, October 2001 (Box 23, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, November 2001 (Box 23, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, December 2001 (Box 23, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, January 2002 (Box 23, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, February 2002 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, March-April 2002 (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, May-June 2002 (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Letters to the University Community, 1990-1994 (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Letters to the University Community, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Letters to the University Community, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 6)
  - Letters to the University Community, 1997-2002 (Box 24, Folder 7)
- Series II. Writing and Speeches, 1963-2002; 21.2 Linear Feet in 48 manuscript boxes and 1 half manuscript box
  This series consists of Oliva's published and unpublished writing (mostly articles) and numerous speeches delivered during his tenure (commencement speeches, speeches to the Board of Trustees, and public lectures). Most of Oliva's published writing was completed prior to his presidency, but it reflects his long-held interests in sports and academic affairs. The vast amount of speeches represents another daily responsibility, the various events, meetings, lectures, and programs that required Oliva's attendance and commentary.
  Arranged into two subseries chronologically.
  - Subseries II.A Writing, 1963-2000
    This subseries consists of published and unpublished writing by Oliva, the majority of which was written prior to Oliva's term as president. Most of the published writing consists of articles in various publications, such as The New York Times and NCAA News, and includes correspondence with publishers, drafts, galleys, and final printed versions. The unpublished writing consists of article drafts and notes.
    - Correspondence and Status Reports, 1986-1991 (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - List of Published Articles, 1986-1990 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Published Writing, circa 1963-October 1986 (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Published Writing, November 1986 (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - Published Writing, December 1986 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Published Writing, January-June 1987 (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Published Writing, July-November 1987 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Published Writing, 1988-1991 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Published Writing, 1992-1993 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Published Writing, Spring 2000 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Unpublished Writing, 1985-1987 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Unpublished Writing, 1989-1991 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Subseries II.B Speeches, 1984-2002
    This subseries consists of the various speeches delivered by Oliva during his presidency, although there are a few speeches from his previous roles. The speeches represent new initiatives, such as NYU in London; university events, including Commencement, award ceremonies, and exhibition openings; and non-university events, such as conferences hosted by other institutions. Many of the speeches are informal and include talking points, outlines, and/or notes.
    - Speech Database, 1986-1999 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Speech Topics, 1990-1991 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Speech Topics, 1992-1995 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - "Lessons in History", circa 1984 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - First Annual Chancellor's Service Awards, May 1985 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Reception for American College of Physicians' Distinguished Teacher Awardee, Saul J. Farber, April 1986 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Faculty Networking Party, May 1986 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Dinner (Draft), November 1986 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Manhattan College Convocation, October 1987 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - "Who Are Our Graduate Students?", February 1988 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Higher Education Seminar Series Talking Points, April 1988 (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Personnel Service Awards, April 1988 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - All-University Convocation, October 1988 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Reception for Soviet Rectors (Draft), March 1989 (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Faculty Networking Luncheon, January 1990 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - "Salute to Benefactors of NYU" Luncheon, April 1990 (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Founders Day, April 1990 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Samuel and May Rudin Community Service Awards, May 1990 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Medical School Facilities Presentation, "Building for the Future: NYU Today", June 1990 (Box 27, Folder 17)
    - New Faculty Reception, October 1990 (Box 27, Folder 18)
    - Guidance Counselor Reception, November 1990 (Box 27, Folder 19)
    - "Teaching Effectiveness", January 1991 (Box 27, Folder 20)
    - Toast to Baroness Mariuccia Zerilli-Marimò, February 1991 (Box 27, Folder 21)
    - Faculty Resource Network Dinner, March 1991 (Box 27, Folder 22)
    - The 99th Frank Norris Pig Dinner, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 23)
    - Il Leone di San Award in Academia, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 24)
    - Urban Research Center, Sports and the City Luncheon, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 25)
    - Alumni Council Dinner, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 26)
    - 18th Annual Student Achievement Awards Luncheon, Association of Black Faculty, Administrators and Staff (ABFAS), May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 27)
    - School of Education, Health, Nursing, and the Arts Professions Valedictory Ceremony, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 28)
    - School of Continuing Education Class Day Exercises, May 1991 (Box 27, Folder 29)
    - Sixth Annual Prism Award Luncheon, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Stern School Pre-Commencement Platform Party, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Tisch School of the Arts Salute to the Class of 1991, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Alumni Pre-Commencement Breakfast, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Commencement, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Gallatin Graduation Exercises, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - School of Medicine, Last Day Exercises, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Law School Convocation, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Optimate Awards, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Ireland House Luncheon, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - President's Council Reception, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - NCAA Regional Seminar, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Salute to Dean Oppenheim, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - Neurons, Vision and Cognition Conference, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Alumni Hall Renaming Reception, May 1991 (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Italian-American Scholarship Association Annual Awards Presentation, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Albert Gallatin Associates Life Induction, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - College of Dentistry Graduation, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Charles Walden Haskins Award Dinner, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 19)
    - Faculty Resource Network Summer Reception, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 20)
    - Omega Chapter, Omicron Kappa Upsilon, Induction Dinner, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 21)
    - Rudin Community Service Awards Presentation and Reception, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 22)
    - 21st Century Club Reception, June 1991 (Box 28, Folder 23)
    - Chancellor's Summer Reception, July 1991 (Box 28, Folder 24)
    - Reception Honoring Mary Schmidt Campbell, August 1991 (Box 28, Folder 25)
    - Dillard University Faculty Conference, August 1991 (Box 28, Folder 26)
    - Gens Antiquissima Italiae: The Etruscans in Umbria Exhibition Opening, September 1991 (Box 28, Folder 27)
    - Opening of School of Continuing Education Film and Video Facility, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Classroom Dedication Reception, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Reception Honoring Dr. John Brademas, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - C-Team Meeting, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Peter Agnew Memorial Lecture, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Kick-Off for Stern School Capital Campaign, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Dedication of Frank J. and Edwardine Tasco House, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Watch Team Seminar, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Breakfast for Bobst Movers, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Stern School Graduate Alumni Association -- Tenth Anniversary Celebration, September 1991 (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - "Voices of the Encounter: The World on the Eve of 1492" Reading, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - "1492-1992 Crossroads of Culture" Dinner, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - Dinner in Honor of Ronald Perelman, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Institute of International Education (IIE) European Rectors Visit to NYU, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Dinner for Honorable Edward I. Koch, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - United Way/NYU Community Fund Kick-Off Breakfast, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - University Settlement Awards, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Dedication of Bram House and Farkas House, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. Scholars/Graduate and Professional Opportunity Fellows Reception, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - Alumni Federation and Medallion Society Annual Dinner, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Parent's Day, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Vaclav Havel Honorary Degree and Luncheon, October 1991 (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Reception for Alice Huang, October 1991 (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Introduction for Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, James Madison Lecturer, October 1991 (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - New Faculty Reception, October 1991 (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Reception for Professor Richard Schechner, October 1991 (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Opening of Claudette Colbert Film Festival, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Fall College President's Media Dinner, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Varsity Club Annual Awards Dinner, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Luncheon Honoring Aleksy II, Patriarch of Russia, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Reading Recovery Program, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Introduction for Milton Petrie Lecture by Allen Questrom -- "Surviving the Retail Revolution", November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - A Morning at Washington Square, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Inaugural Address as President of NYU, November 1991 (Box 30, Folder 12)